[
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 2001,
        "question": "<p>What are the characteristics of feudalism? <br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><em><strong>The characteristics of feudalism are as follows: </strong></em></p><p>(i) It is based on land ownership.</p><p>(ii) Ownership of land is vested in the king, monarch or emperor.</p><p>(iii)The serfs (tenants) pay their overlords' annual tributes in money or kind.</p><p>(iv) The overlords are duty bound to protect the serfs.</p><p>(v) Feudal tenants give military service to the overlords.</p><p>(vi) Only a vassal of the lord can receive land.</p><p>(vii) Feudalism is characterized by close personal bond between the lords and serfs.</p><p>(viii) A vassal keeps the land as long as he performs his feudal duties, e.g. payment of tributes, military service to his overlord.</p><p>(ix) The land goes back to the lord when the vassal dies without an heir.</p><p>(x) The monarch is the lawmaker, judge and commander over his vassals. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 2001,
        "question": "<p>Describe the basic features of a democratic state. <br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>The basic features of a democratic state include: </em></strong></p><p>(i) A democratic state holds periodic elections to elect representatives into the various legislative houses. </p><p>(ii) It provides equal opportunity for citizens to participate in the decisions of the government.</p><p>(iii) Under democratic dispensation, fundamental human rights are guaranteed.</p><p>(iv) The rights of the minority are also guaranteed.</p><p>(v) Free and fair elections are conducted by creating an independent electoral commission which updates the electoral register, conducts election through secret ballot etc. In Nigeria, this is presently done by the Independent National Electoral Commission (INEC).</p><p>(vi) There is the formation of political parties in a democratic state.</p><p>(vii) There is the existence of opposition party to serve as a watchdog of the government.</p><p>(viii)There is an independent judiciary.</p><p>(ix)In a democratic state there is the rule of law.</p><p>(x)The franchise is open to all on the basis of universal adult suffrage.</p><p>(xi) There is provision of special procedures to amend parts of the constitution, e.g. creation of new states, impeachment of the president etc.</p><p>(xii) There is the supremacy of the constitution.</p><p>(xiii) There is the freedom of expression and the existence of a free press.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 2001,
        "question": "<p>Why do some countries adopt unitary system of government? <br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>Some countries adopt unitary system of government because of the following factors or reasons: </em></strong></p><p>(i) The countries are small in terms of territory and population.</p><p>(ii) They are relatively homogeneous and there is absence of marked ethnic inequalities.</p><p>(iii) They have limited skilled personnel and economic resources.</p><p>(iv) They have identical political culture and history, i.e., common historical and political experience in administration.</p><p>(v) They have the desire for the preservation of national unity or identity and values.</p><p>(vi) Unitary system of government is simple and cheap to operate.</p><p>(vii) It also facilitates quick decision-making. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 2001,
        "question": "<p>How can the revenue of Local Authorities in your country be improved?<br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>The revenue of local authorities can be improved through the following methods:</em></strong></p><p>(i) Grants from the central government should be increased.</p><p>(ii) Grants to local authorities should be paid regularly and promptly to encourage investment in viable projects.</p><p>(iii) Local rates should be reviewed and where it is low, it should be increased to cater for inflation.</p><p>(iv) The revenue collecting sector should be overhauled and only qualified officers with proven integrity should be responsible for collecting revenue.</p><p>(v) The local authorities should be allowed by the central government to raise loans more easily from financial institutions.</p><p>(vi) More revenue yielding projects should be embarked upon, e.g. agriculture, housing projects etc.</p><p>(vii) The local people should be well educated or mobilized to pay their rates regularly.</p><p>(viii)There should be regular auditing of the accounts of the local authorities. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 2001,
        "question": "<p>Enumerate the methods used by pressure groups to achieve their objectives. <br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>The methods used by pressure groups to achieve their objectives are: </em></strong></p><p>(i) Demonstration / Protest: Pres-sure groups can demonstrate or protest against a government policy through rioting, hijacking and holding people as hostages.</p><p>(ii) Work-to-rule: No extra work is done apart from the normal working period.</p><p>(iii) Strike: Pressure groups may refuse to work to back up their demand.</p><p>(iv) Debates and Symposia I Workshop: These are organised to educate the people on their work and also their stand on some issues.</p><p>(v) Lobbying: This is done through legislators to persuade policy makers when policies are being made.</p><p>(vi) Boycott: Sometimes, pressure groups refuse to co-operate with the authorities until their demands are met.</p><p>(vii) Sending a delegation: Pressure groups select some of their members to discuss their problems with the government or decision-makers.</p><p>(viii) Propaganda / Letters to the press: Pressure groups write letters to the press to educate the public and to show their stand on important policies.</p><p>(ix) Special publications: This is done either in the press, handbills or a booklet to publicize their action.</p><p>(x) Presentation of gift: In West Africa, a common feature of pressure groups is to present gifts (gratifications) to policy makers to influence their decisions on certain issues.</p><p>(xi) Alliance with political parties and candidates who are perceived to be sympathetic to their cause.</p><p>(xii) Ultimatum: This is the final statement of conditions which pressure groups issue to be accepted by the government without which action they deem necessary will be taken. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 2001,
        "question": "<p>How did the people of any one British West African territory govern themselves before the advent of colonial rule?<br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>Before the advent of colonial rule the people of British West African territory, e.g. Nigeria governed themselves in the following ways: </em></strong></p><p>(i) The people were governed by custom, rules and norms.</p><p>(ii) The paramount chief was at the apex of the administration.</p><p>(iii)The chiefs and council of elders made laws, i.e., they were the lawmakers.</p><p>(iv) The age grades executed laws</p><p>(v) The traditional rulers and elders exercised legislative, executive and judicial powers, i.e., there was no separation of powers.</p><p>(vi) The chief priests and the secret societies performed religious functions and checked arbitrary use of power by chiefs.</p><p>(vii) Queen mothers and palace women performed important roles, e.g. 5. settling disputes among women, advising the chiefs etc.</p><p>(viii) The commoners also performed important roles, e.g. 6. manual labour for community development and defence.</p><p>(ix) Revenue was raised through tributes and taxes.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 2001,
        "question": "<p>State how the British colonial policies contributed to the rise of nationalism in West Africa. <br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>The British colonial policies contributed to the rise of nationalism in West Africa in many ways. These include:</em></strong></p><p> (i) The crown-colony policy was not acceptable to the nationalists, e.g. both the legislative and executive councils were dominated by British officials. Only illiterate African chiefs were nominated as members of the legislative council.</p><p>(ii) The land law was unfavourable to the chiefs and people.</p><p>(iii) The whites adopted colour bar and social segregation, e.g. housing estates, recreational facilities, hospital and schools.</p><p>(iv) Economic inequalities between 9. the whites and the indigenes especially in commercial enterprises contributed a lot to the rise of nationalism, e.g. granting of loans by banks, the activities of companies like UAC, UTC and P.Z.</p><p>(v) There was little or no opportunities for the advancement of the Africans in the public service.</p><p>(vi) There was inequality in wages between whites and natives especially in commercial enterprises were.</p><p>(vii) Provision of educational facilities through missionaries made the Africans politically conscious.</p><p>(viii)There opportunities for the Africans to participate in government through constitutional developments.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 2001,
        "question": "<p><strong><em>Describe the main features of the 1946 Richards Constitution of Nigeria. </em></strong><br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>The main features of the 1946 Richards Constitution of Nigeria were:</em></strong></p><p>(i) Certain services were reserved for the central government and were financed by the central government, e.g. railways, army, post and telegraphs.</p><p>(ii) The revenues of Nigeria were apportioned to each region in the form of bulk grants</p><p>(iii) The native authorities were linked with the regional assembly and through the latter to the central legislative council.</p><p>(iv) The regional councils were used as electoral colleges for representation in the legislative council.</p><p>(v) Members of the central legislative council were at the same time members of the regional council; the central legislature had regional instead of national outlook.</p><p>(vi) It brought an African unofficial majority into the central legislative council.</p><p>(vii) It brought the North and South together under one legislature.</p><p>(viii) It led to the creation of regional assemblies with limited powers to legislate on minor matters, subject to the Governor's reserved powers.</p><p>(ix) It granted the North a bicameral legislature, that is, the regional assembly and the regional house of chiefs.</p><p>(x) Nigerians were in the minority in the central executive council.</p><p>(xi) Limited franchise was maintained three representatives were elected for Lagos and one for Calabar.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 2001,
        "question": "<p>Outline the objectives of the National Council of Nigeria and the Cameroons (N.C.N.C.) <br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><em><strong>The objectives of the National Council of Nigeria and the Cameroons (NCNC) were:</strong></em></p><p>(i) To arouse mass interest and obtain overwhelming national support for political reforms</p><p>(ii)To achieve political independence by giving political 18, education to the people of Nigeria</p><p>(iii)To provide the members with medium of expression in order to secure political freedom, economic security, social equality and religious tolerance</p><p>(iv) To advance the interest of the people of 19. Nigeria and the Cameroons under the British mandate</p><p>(v) To organise and collaborate effectively with all its branches throughout the country</p><p>(vi) To promote higher education as well as compulsory free education for the children.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 2001,
        "question": "<p>What were the causes of the 1975 military coup de'tat in Nigeria? <br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><em><strong>The causes of 1975 military coup de 'tat in Nigeria were:</strong></em></p><p>(i) Corruption: The government was corrupt and it encouraged corrupt practices by contractors, government officials etc.</p><p>(ii) The government was not able to arrive at a definite figure for 1973 population census. Government announced only provisional figures which were not generally acceptable.</p><p>(iii) There was a change in the proposed date for return to civil rule.</p><p>(iv) There was scarcity of essential commodities due to port congestion.</p><p>(v) Indecision on the part of the then government on major policies of government e.g. redeployment of governors and permanent secretaries contributed to the coup.</p><p>(vi) The government disregarded-public opinion on some major national issues, e.g. creation of more states.</p><p>(vii) Members of the armed forces got disillusioned with the government.</p><p>(viii) There was mismanagement of public funds. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 11,
        "year": 2001,
        "question": "<p>(a) What is foreign policy?</p><p>(b) Outline the basic factors that influence Nigeria's foreign policy. <br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) Foreign policy refers to the strategy and tactics employed by a state in conducting her relationship with other states while pursuing her interest.</p><p><em><strong>(b) The factors that influence Nigeria's foreign policy are:</strong></em></p><p>(i) The population, land mass and the quality of human resources of Nigeria affect her foreign policy.</p><p>(ii) The economic resources available to Nigeria, e.g. mineral re-sources and agricultural products affect foreign policy.</p><p>(iii)The commitments of previous governments, e.g. treaties and pacts, affect foreign policy.</p><p>(iv) The ideological disposition of the rulers affect foreign policy as countries tend to relate more with those countries with similar ideologies.</p><p>(v) The military strength of Nigeria (i.e. size of the army and the quality) influences her foreign policy.</p><p>(vi) The industrial strength of Nigeria influences her choice of trading partners, e.g. electricity supply to Niger, Gas to Ghana, Republic of Benin and Togo.</p><p>(vii) Public opinion on issues can bring changes in government foreign policy, e.g. Anglo — Nigeria pact of 1962.</p><p> (viii) The geographical location of a country also exerts some influence on its foreign policy. Africa for example is described as centre piece of Nigeria's foreign policy.</p><p>(ix) Historical background of the country also affects her foreign policy, e.g. Nigeria's membership of the Commonwealth.</p><p>(x) Types of government, e.g. military or democratic government, can affect foreign policy .<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 12,
        "year": 2001,
        "question": "<p>Highlight the functions of the Assembly of Heads of State and Governments of the Organization of African Unity (0.A. U.). <br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p>The functions or roles of the Assembly of Heads of State and Governments of the Organization of African Unity (0.A.U) are: (i) It acts as the highest decision-making organ of the O.A.U.</p><p>(ii) It discusses matters of common interest of member states.</p><p>(iii) It coordinates and harmonises the general policies of the organisation.</p><p>(iv) It appoints the important officers of the organisation such as the Secretary General.</p><p>(v) It has power to establish specialized commissions.</p><p>(vi) It examines and reviews the structure, composition and functions of all other organs and specialized agencies of the organisation.</p><p>(vii) It considers reports from the secretariat.</p><p>(viii) It appoints adhoc committees to settle disputes involving member states.</p><p>(ix) It decides on the admission of new members.</p><p>(x) It considers and approves proposals for amendments of the charter of the organisation.</p><p>(xi) It approves the regulations governing the function and conditions of services of the Administrative Secretary General, his assistants and other staff. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    }
]